I, James Vance, do solemnly swear that I
will support and defend the Constitution
of the United States. So help me God.
>> Congratulations, Mr. Vice President.
>> We're the senior [music] partner. We're
the world's superpower. That's the way
that it works.
>> This is not just theft of the American
people's money. This is also theft of
critical services that the American
people rely on. This is a [music]
problem that has festered in this
country for far too long. You stop
socialism by making people's lives
better. [music] And that's what we're
trying to do every single day.
>> We got to take care of business this
November, then we'll worry about [music]
what comes next.
>> Please welcome Vice President J. D.
Vance. [music]
[music]
All right. [applause]
Nice to see you, Mr. Vice President. How
are you?
>> I'm good. I'm good. I Jason, I I caught
the very tail end of that panel
discussion and you you were asking
somebody about how their life had
changed. I couldn't see who it was, but
asking how their life had changed cuz
they had been in the big house, which it
appears to me you meant prison, but I I
thought you were talking about the
Michigan football team stadium
[laughter] they played. So, very
different understanding of what you were
talking about and what was actually
going on.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, well, it's great it's great to have
you back. We always appreciate that you
take the time to join the besties and
have a very candid, honest discussion.
This is your, I think, third or fourth
time on the program. Uh, and it's a
great time to be on the program because
you're halfway through uh your term
approximately and the midterms are
coming up. maybe you could assess what's
went really well for and what you're
proud of with this uh first two years
and then let's get into some things that
maybe your own constituents
um are not happy with and uh let's start
with the positive. What do you think
you've accomplished in these first two
years?
Well, look, I I think the the two things
that I'm most proud of are first of all,
we actually got control of the southern
border, but started to reverse the flow
of illegal immigration, which is about 3
million lower today than it was when we
came into office. Obviously, there's a
lot more to do, but if you look at the
history of Western governments in the
post-war era, they open the border. They
invite border invasions, but they never
actually reverse it. At best, they slow
it down. I think President Trump was the
first president in my lifetime to
actually reverse that flow of illegal
immigration. I'm extremely proud of
that. I'm also proud, as you guys know,
I've been obsessively focused on this.
[applause]
I I I've been obsessively focused on
this for a long time, which is the idea
of re-industrializing and recapitalizing
the the the manufacturing base of the
United States of America. And, you know,
this was a bipartisan consensus that
leaned into globalization that sort of
bought into this idea that you could
have a prosperous economy that was built
entirely around services, tech, and
finance. And the reality of course is
that to have a truly prosperous economy,
you still have to make stuff. And I
think Donald Trump understood that
better than anybody else. Obviously, it
takes a long time uh to rebuild the
manufacturing base of the country. But
if you look at the trillions of dollars
of new investment, the new construction,
uh the new manufacturing facilities
being built, I do think that you're
seeing the obvious signs that over the
past 18 months, we've reversed a 40-year
trend. Now, Rome wasn't built in a day.
going to take longer to fully undo the
damage wrought by the last 40 years. But
the fact that we're actually on the
right pathway is a signature achievement
of Donald Trump. But I think it's the
thing that he will be remembered for
even more than the border. He will be
remembered for ending the sort of
consensus around globalization and
actually enacting policies that get us
on the on the right track. Again,
>> I think we we all agree with those two
and just absolute congratulations on
that. Uh you guys have crushed it. I
think we all concur. um your
constituents, the people who voted for
you are extremely frustrated about two
issues. Let's just tackle them head-on.
The first is you promised us you
wouldn't start a foreign war. You
promised us you wouldn't start a foreign
war in the Middle East specifically. And
then you promised you would get
inflation under control. You haven't
been able to get inflation under
control. Still 3 or 4% this year. It's
not looking good. And Americans,
specifically the people who voted for
you, Mr. vice president are very upset
about starting this war. What is your
message to them? How do these two issues
get resolved? Because people are very
unhappy about it.
>> Yeah. So, so Jason, I understand that
and I certainly hear from people. And
what I would say first of all is we
invite people into the coalition who
disagree with us. You don't have to
agree with us on every single issue. But
on the war specifically, what I I would
say is look, the president came in and
yes, he wanted to keep the United States
out of foreign entanglements. He also
said that he was committed to Iran not
having a nuclear weapon. And I think
that wanting to keep the United States
out of foreign entanglements does not
mean that you can never use the military
in order to accomplish the American
people's objectives. Now, all that said,
despite the fact that we did accomplish
a substantial destruction, not just of
their nuclear program, but also of the
Iranian conventional military, we've
seen the Iranians shooting at commercial
shipping even in the midst of peace
negotiations. And I think the president
has actually done the responsible thing
here, which is to try to ensure that
world energy markets, despite Iranian
terrorism, continue to get that flow of
oil and gas. And so what I would say to
anybody who's frustrated right now is
the alternative here, which is the
United States effectively says to the
Middle East, you're on your own, would
mean necessarily a worldwide energy
crisis so long as the Iranians keep on
shooting at shipping, which we know
that's exactly what they would do. So, I
think the president is taking the
responsible course of action. He's
protecting America's assets in the
region while also ensuring that world
energy markets continue to get a supply
of oil and natural gas. And you on the
inflation, Jason, I I think we've made a
lot of progress. To my point earlier,
Rome was not built in a day, but you
know, under the Biden administration, we
had inflation, I think, at 9 12%
annualized. That's the highest rate in
about 48 years. You're right. three and
a half% is still too high, but you've
seen substantial progress and of course
we're going to keep on making progress.
I guess my pitch to the American people
and to to your listeners certainly would
be do you want to reelect the people who
have made substantial progress accepting
there's still a lot of work to be done
or do you want to go back to the people
who caused the problem in the first
place? And obviously I'm biased but I
think that you should elect the people
who have actually made substantial
progress while recognizing a lot more
progress needs to happen. Mr. Mr. Vice
President, the um [applause]
one of the other things many of us were
excited about with this incoming
administration was addressing the fiscal
deficit. Uh it seems to become more
apparent to markets that this is
potentially a risk to the to the the US
um dollar over time. The the 30-year I
think is around 5.2% now. What's your
view? And you know, when the
administration came in, there was an
effort with Doge. Uh, but it's been very
hard to get congressional action to take
the steps necessary to reduce the
deficit. Maybe you can share the
administration's view, your view on what
can we do to write the fiscal course for
the federal government now and over
time.
>> Yeah, look, it's a very important and
fair question. I mean, I I think that in
fundamentally the the anti-fraud efforts
that I've been focused on, we've saved
about $250 billion of the American
taxpayers money that would have
otherwise gone to fraudsters. And in the
scale of a 7 trillion federal budget,
obviously $250 billion isn't the whole
thing, but it's a lot and it's something
that we're very proud of. I think we
have to continue to sort of just
tackling the basic fraud and waste
that's endemic to our government. And of
course, we are going to need some real
bipartisan legislative solutions to give
markets confidence. Not just that we're
going to be serious about the deficit,
but that hopefully the president who
comes after and the Congress that comes
after is going to be serious about the
deficit. I think fundamentally the
problem here, and I I think what the
markets are responding to at this moment
is the perception that neither
congressional Republicans or Democrats
are serious about the debt and the
deficit. Obviously, I think the
administration, I'm biased. I think that
we are serious about this issue. If you
look at what Scott Bassen, who I'm going
to meet with in a couple of hours,
actually, uh what Scott Bassen has
talked about is, you know, let's be
realistic. We have we we inherited a $2
trillion fiscal deficit. And you're not
going to get back to a balanced budget
by cutting $2 trillion out of a $7
trillion budget overnight. What you can
do is you can cut smartly but also grow
and get the economy in a position where
that fiscal deficit is closer to 3% of
GDP. Now yes we got to make more
progress but if you look at what Scott
has done at the Treasury I think that we
are on pace to get to a point where we
can get the fiscal deficit to a
sustainable level and then of course you
get it to a sustainable level and you
can continue to make progress from
there. But it is certainly a very
serious problem, something that we're
very focused on. And I guess what I
would say to to markets is we've got a
secretary of the Treasury, but also a
president who are very focused on the
problem, but it's going to require a
long-term solution. Ideally, something
with some bipartisan consensus, which is
something we'll have to see about
because let's be honest, uh, a lot of
people in Congress, not just Democrats,
but a lot of people in Congress have not
shown a willingness to be serious about
spending. We have to change that.
>> Let's, um, let's maybe double click on
that, Mr. Vice President. There's one
one of the ways that we can get out of
this is through growth and productivity
growth. But there is this crazy dynamic
where it just seems like there are
forces many inside the United States um
that try to slow us down whether it's
data centers and you may have heard
yesterday but the president called in
and tried to help debunk it with Jensen
Meta uh was here debunking uh Microsoft
was here but it just seems like a
whack-a-mole problem of trying to
actually get the truth out. just talk to
us about
how we've ended up in this situation
where there are these forces that are
trying to effectively
lie or fear-monger to try to take power.
>> Yeah. So, this is something I think we
could spend an hour talking about. I
know we don't have that much time,
Chimath, but but fundamentally when I
see the backlash to data centers, what I
see is the the the the necessary the
inevitable consequence of the United
States not building enough power for a
generation. And so we've talked about
this before, but if if when I talk to
people, I obviously sort of I'm out
there campaigning a lot. I'm talking to
people a lot. Uh there there's
definitely some basic nimiism in the
anti-data center thing, but there's
also, you know, you talk to a guy who a
year ago his power bill was $290 a month
and now it's $580 a month. And the
reality is that in blue states where
we've made it impossible to build
additional electricity generation,
you're seeing a backlash when people
start paying additional power costs.
Now, my response to that is you can't
just stop building because of it. What
you've got to do is build the things
that you need, specifically power. So,
you know, Elon talks about this all the
time, but I talk about it, too. If you
look at the amount of power generated by
the PRC, the People's Republic of China,
and compare it to the amount of power
generated by the United States of
America in 2005, they crossed the line,
meaning they started to generate just a
little bit more power than we did in
2005. And since then, we have
effectively flatlined. and the PRC now
generates three times as much
electricity as the United States of
America does. I think that a lot of our
problems um are downstream of that
fundamental problem and we just have to
build more. We have to build more power.
We I mean, you know, I I think we have
to have this vision in the United States
of electricity that is too cheap to
meter. And that's I think the way that
you push back against some of this
ridiculous um you know sort of
anti-building power comes from the
failure to generate the electricity that
we need. And I I just I don't understand
how we ever got here as a country. I
think the environmental movement
obviously has a lot to do with it, but
we've just got to build more power and
that's how we solve this problem
fundamentally. And then you know
obviously some of this gets into the
broader AI stuff Jamaimoth and you know
the president I think is very rightly
asking the question why is it that the
people who are at the frontier of the AI
economy are throwing up their hands and
saying well we've built Frankenstein and
the solution to Frankenstein apparently
is to create a one world governance
structure for artificial intelligence.
What I would say to those people, if
you're building Frankenstein, stop. Or
maybe build, you know, if if the cat is
out of the bag, then build the defensive
mechanism against Frankenstein. And, you
know, I I I I I don't know Daario well.
I I've read everything that he said over
the past couple of weeks. Everybody that
I know tells me that he's very earnest,
that this is a deeply held belief. It's
not cynical. It's not about regulatory
capture, that he genuinely cares about
this. But at the same time, I talk to
tech companies. I'm sure you guys talk
to a lot more tech companies than I do.
At the same time that you have this sort
of cyber hacking tool that's come out of
Anthropic's newest models, you have
companies that are desperate for the
defensive mechanisms to defend against
that cyber hacking tool and they're
being denied access to it. So if you're
going to create Frankenstein, don't come
to the government and say we need
regulation. look inward and accept that
if you're building Frankenstein, number
one, you should stop. And number two,
when the companies come to you and say,
"We need the tools to fight back against
Frankenstein," give them those tools.
>> Right. Oh,
>> it's incredibly common sensical.
Uh Brad and then maybe Sachs. Yep.
>> Mr. Vice President, great to see you. Um
you know, the president called in
yesterday. He's on top of the AI issue.
you you're working for somebody who's
the most incredibly entrepreneurial and
risk-taking president perhaps in the
last 50 years. I just had a at a you
know personal level how is it working
with somebody who is willing to take the
risk that you know some people you know
Jason criticized some of the things that
haven't happened in the first 20 months
but the fact of the matter is unlike a
lot of people who occupy that office who
are just looking to stay the course and
take the safe path he's taking a lot of
risks and then you have to help explain
some of those I would I would put Trump
accounts in that category the main
street agenda But, you know, just talk
to us a little bit at a personal level
how working with him, how hard it is to
keep up with his energy, his enthusiasm,
his entrepreneurialism.
>> Yeah, Brad, you know him well. He he
sleeps less than any person that I've
ever met. I don't sleep that much, but I
certainly sleep more than him. You know,
Scott Bassin and I always joke that
he'll call us at 2:30 in the morning and
he'll say, "Were you up?" And it's like,
"No, sir, I wasn't, but I am now. So,
let's let's talk about what's on your
mind." Uh, he's working at all hours of
the day. But but your point, Brad, is is
very well taken. He is certainly willing
to take risks. And I I I think, you
know, you ask what it's like working for
a guy like that. Well, one, it's never
boring. But two, he's constantly
probing, are we taking the easy path or
are we taking the right path? And yes,
maybe this thing is going to cause some
political backlash or maybe the payoff
is not going to be obvious until, you
know, two years from now, 5 years from
now, 10 years from now. But I think it's
the exact right mindset. You know, one
one of the frustrations I've had just
looking at the economy, you know, pretty
much my entire life is there's there's
been this division between true
entrepreneurs and managers, between
bureaucrats and people who are genuinely
innovative and willing to take risks. I
think that we've had way too many
caretaker presidents during my lifetime.
Uh, frankly, way too many caretaker CEOs
and not enough people who are genuinely
innovative and willing to take risks.
Obviously, he gets criticized for it
from time to time, but I'd much rather
have a president who's willing to take
those risks, who's willing to take on
the big projects. It's the only way I
think you're going to reverse America's
long-term decline is to be willing to
take those risks. Thank God for the past
18 months, we've had a president willing
to do just that.
[applause]
>> Uh Mr. Vice President, uh Jake forgot to
ask uh his normal gotcha question on
H1Bs. [laughter] So, um,
>> well, that's because they took my advice
and they raised the price. You were in
sync on that one.
>> Um, it, you know, it's an issue that the
tech community cares about. At the same
time, we have learned that the program
was riddled with fraud. I'm curious what
can you give us an update on, you know,
where do those efforts stand? What, you
know, what's happening with that the
H-1Bs?
>> Yeah. No, this is the the vin diagram
overlap of Jason Calcconis and Steven
Miller. It's a very small area.
[laughter]
But but look man, we we we looked at the
fraud in the system and we said, you
know, one, Congress is not going to pass
a law changing this, there just isn't
the political will to do it. So what are
the things that we can do
administratively to ensure that if a
tech company is going to try to get an
H-1B visa, it it's an actual genius.
It's a person that is going to
significantly enrich the tech ecosystem
or the American economy. you know,
you're not just replacing one accountant
who makes $60,000 with a lower wage
foreign accountant who makes $45,000 a
year. That is not what the program
exists for. And so, we came up with this
idea to impose $100,000 fee. We're also
looking at various ways of preventing
companies that use H-1B visas from
laying off a bunch of American workers.
Uh so, you know, one of the the things
that I find just shocking about this is
you'll have a company that applies for
an H-1B and they'll say, "Oh, we're
desperate for workers. we can't find the
workers. And then you go and look at
their history and they've laid off 5,000
people. Well, that's ridiculous. If
you're laying off American workers, you
shouldn't be going to the market
searching for foreign workers to replace
them. So, we're doing a lot within the
confines, of course, of what we're
allowed to do legally. We've gotten sued
on some of this stuff, but I think
fundamentally we're on the right on both
the law and the policy. The H1B should
not exist to replace American workers
with low-wage foreigners. It should
exist to enrich the American economy.
And that's exactly what we're trying to
make sure it does.
>> Mr. Vice President, can I can I ask um
you're you're I I think you're you're
titled the frauds are now. And just
going back to the the um the deficit
question, every week we're seeing these
videos. You know, we've got Nick Shirley
here this afternoon. I think he really
started this trend of some of the
citizen journalists going out and trying
to find the fraud in the system
themselves. And every week there's a new
story that's being uncovered that's just
mind-blowing. tens of billions of
dollars over and over again. How much
fraud do you think there? And and you
know this California highspeed rail,
there was a guy that got paid half a
billion dollars for not working. Some
billionaire in Italy who owns a football
team. I couldn't believe it. I I tracked
all this stuff and I'm like it just your
head starts to spin. How much of our $7
trillion federal spending do you think
is tied up in fraud, in this kind of
system of waste and this corruption? And
what's your sense of the scale of the
the problem?
Yeah. So, to two quick things on that.
First of all, you know, Elon during the
height of Doge said that it was 20%,
that's $1.4 trillion. Uh whether it's
10% or 20%, you're talking about
something on the scale of hundreds and
hundreds of billions of dollars. The
biggest problem with finding fraud is is
actually that the states where it's
worst are also the states that have the
least willingness to cooperate with what
we're doing. So when you look at some of
the bigger ticket items for fraud, you
know, you're looking at Medicare fraud
in California, people who are illegal,
people who aren't even like human
beings. They're just like a completely
madeup, you know, shell of a person. Uh
but but unfortunately, the the state of
California is not actually helping us
fight back against that particular
fraud. or we know that there are
hundreds [snorts] of thousands maybe
more illegal aliens in Illinois, New
York and California who are on Medicaid.
That obviously is billions and billions
of dollars to provide health care uh to
those people. So the the the basic fraud
that exists is the big programs in
states that have allowed themselves to
be overrun by illegal immigration.
Another very good example, and this was
shocking to me when we came in and
started doing this work, is the way the
SNAP program, this is the food stamp
program that ensures that low-income
Americans have access to food that they
need. Obviously, one of the most
important things that we do in the
federal government is make sure that,
you know, poor kids can eat. But that
program is rife with fraud in part
because the way it works is, you know,
California bills us once a month for the
cost of their SNAP program. It's seven
or eight or 9 billion depending on the
month that we're talking about. So what
happens is the federal government wires
$9 billion to California, no questions
asked. So, it's not an exaggeration to
say that we have no ability to know who
is even on the SNAP program, whether
they're a real human being, whether
they're a legal resident of the United
States of America. And when we go to the
big blue states and say, "Why don't you
help us just confirm basic eligibility?"
We get totally push back. We we get no
cooperation on this basic fact of good
governance, confirming eligibility for
federal programs. So my guess is that if
the number is $700 billion, a few
hundred billion of that is in the blue
states and we could deal with it just by
checking eligibility criteria. We're
working on innovative ways to force
that. But it's actually legally much
harder than it should be to force the
blue states to comply with some basic
anti-fraud initiatives.
>> Uh JD, before we wrap here, I want to
ask you another hard question. Um this
one about our relationship with the
state of Israel and the president's
relationship with BB Netanyahu. Um many
people in the Republican party, MAGA are
now moving to a new party, America
first, America only. There's a rise in
anti-semitism and there's a persistent
belief amongst a lot of the people on
the right that maybe our foreign policy
is too influenced by the state of Israel
or BB Netanyahu. Can you take us into
the relationship right now where it
stands uh and and and the you know the
administration's position on
collaborating with Israel on a lot of
these military activities?
>> Yeah. You know what the president has
said, Jason, is obviously Israel has
been an important partner when it comes
to military technology, when it comes to
intelligence sharing, but also sometimes
the United States doesn't always agree
with Israel. And I think that more than
frankly any president in the last 40
years, he has shown a willingness uh to
actually part ways with BB Netanyahu
when he feels like the interests of the
American people are different from the
interests of of the government of
Israel. And I find it a little ironic,
Jason, that you have Democrats
criticizing Donald Trump for his
relationship with BB when Donald Trump
is the one president of the last 40
years who's been willing to say, you
know what, yeah, BB's a good partner,
but also BB and I have a different
opinion on this, or BB's wrong about
this, or maybe BB's right about this
from the perspective of Israel, but the
American people need us to go in a
different direction. So I I I just think
that rooting this relationship like all
relationships in America's interest is
the way to actually have a rational
conversation here because when you're
talking about whether a given policy is
in America's interest and you keep
yourself laser focused on that, I think
that's how you make sure that the
American people know that you're
fighting for them. But I also think that
it allows us to actually rationally
focus and force ourselves to have a
conversation about when something that
maybe sounded good or maybe has become a
cliche or a slogan for the past 20 or 30
years. Well, maybe we have to do
something different now. And I I think
that that's how we have to approach not
just this relationship but all
relationships. By by the way, you you
see a similar push back when the
president makes the argument that he's
made about NATO, which is yes, obviously
a lot of important relationships, a lot
of important partnerships in NATO, but
that doesn't mean that we're going to
completely make our European foreign
policy subservient to NATO in the same
way that we cannot let our Middle
Eastern foreign policy be subservient to
the state of Israel. We're going to work
with people when we work with them.
We're going to disagree when we
disagree. And we're going to pursue
America's interest. That's the only way
to have a rational foreign policy.
>> I know Trum wants to get one last
question in here. Um, just before he
does, uh, tell us, how's Marco Rubio
doing in his job so far? Can you rate
his performance in the first two years?
>> He's doing great, man. I love Marco.
Jason, the the funniest media narrative
is that somehow Marco and I are like
hyper competitive and we sit around like
thinking about, you know, how we're
going to run for president against each
other in 2028. Like I I literally What
time is it right now? It's 2:25. I have
a call with Marco in five minutes. So
Chimat's got to ask his question first.
I got to answer it quickly and then
Marco and I have to go do the business
of the American people. He's a great
dude. He's a great human being. He's
doing a great job, too.
>> So maybe maybe as we wrap, um there's a
very consequential midterm coming up. I
think uh a poll on one day will say that
the Republicans are going to keep, you
know, everything as is. the poll on the
other day say it's going to be a
socialist sweep of America. It's very
complicated, but can you just give us
some insight into what's actually
happening on the ground and what is the
message that needs to be delivered so
that folks can uh come to the right
conclusion November?
>> You know, I guess I have two basic
messages there is a lot of good that
we've done over the past 18 months. We
cut taxes bigly. We cut taxes on
overtime, social security, and tips.
Those are tax cuts for middle American
workers, not just for the elites in in
Washington and New York City. Uh we've
had an amazing success with the border
with immigration. We've pursued H-1B
reform that prioritizes American workers
over foreign nationals. There's a lot of
good that's been done, but there's a lot
of work left to do. Don't give power to
the people who cause the problems that
we're fixing. give us another chance or
give us another couple of years to
continue to work on the amazing things
that we've been doing for the past 2
years. And the second argument I'd make
is even if you don't agree with us on
every issue, the other party is consumed
by craziness. They're consumed by people
who want to steal everything, who want
to give the country over to illegal
aliens and criminals. They actively brag
about about it. I mean, I've heard a lot
of crazy stuff, guys, over the past, you
know, few years in politics. But when I
heard somebody running for Congress in
New York say that July 4th was about the
liberation of Puerto Rico and Palestine,
I thought to myself, this person needs
to be checked into a mental hospital
hospital, not given a seat in Congress.
So to the American people, I'd say send
these people packing. Put them in the
middle hospital. Do not put them in
Congress. Because even if you don't
agree with us on every policy issue, at
least we're motivated by common sense
and American interest, they're just
motivated by left-wing interest groups
and radicalism, and they're going to do
a very bad job if we give them power.
>> All right, ladies and gentlemen, Vice
President J.
>> Thank you all. Good to see you guys.
[music]